现在我们要看一个有六个关节或六个自由度的机器人
Now we're going to look at a robot with six joints or six degrees of freedom and this
是一个三维移动的机器人。我将从加载模型开始
is a robot that moves in three dimensions. I'm going to start by loading a model for
Puma560机器人在工作区中创建了许多机器人。最重要的
the Puma 560 robot and that creates a number of robots in the workspace. Most important
这些是变量P560，这是一个表示对象的MATLAB对象。有
of these is the variable P560, this is a MATLAB object that represents an object. There are
还有一些其他变量，这些变量代表特定的关节角度配置QZ
a few other variables as well and these represent particular joint angle configurations, QZ
例如，长度为6的向量全部为零，它表示零的集合
for instance is a vector of length six with all zeros and it represents the set of zero
这个特定机器人的关节角度。
joint angles for this particular robot.
机器人对象有很多方法和方法之一;情节方法，允许
The robot objects have got a lot of methods and one of the methods; the plot method, allows
我们来查看一个机器人的配置，所以这里是特定机器人的全部
us to view the configuration of a robot, so here is that particular robot when all the
关节角度等于零。我可以从许多不同的观点来看待这个问题
joint angles are equal to zero. I can look at this from a number of different viewpoints
并看到机器人，我们也可以在这里看到机器人末端执行器坐标系
and see the robot and we can see also the robot end effector co-ordinate frame here
显示机器人末端执行器的X，Y和Z轴。
showing the X, Y and Z axes of the robot end effector.
现在我们谈论的是反向运动学，所以我希望机器人去一个特定的
Now we're talking about inverse kinematics so I want the robot to go to a particular
姿势，我要定义。首先，我要定义它的翻译
pose and I'm going to define that. First of all I'm going to define it's translational
使用函数transl的组件，我想要一个0.6坐标的坐标，一个Y坐标
component using the function transl and I want an X co-ordinate of 0.6, a Y co-ordinate
0.1和Z坐标为0，现在我需要给它一些方向。我做到了
of 0.1 and a Z co-ordinate of 0 and now I need to give it some orientation. And I do
通过指定其角色，俯仰角和偏航角。我希望角色角度为0，我想要
that by specifying its role, pitch and yaw angles. I want the role angle to be 0, I want
桨距角为180度，我希望偏航角为0度，我指定
the pitch angle to be 180 degrees and I want the yaw angle to be 0 degrees and I specify
我用度数单位给出了角度。这是同质转换
that I have given the angles in terms of unit of degrees. And here is the homogeneous transformation
表示我感兴趣的姿势的矩阵。
matrix representing the pose that I'm interested in.
现在让我们看看那个特定的姿势，我可以将姿势叠加到图中
Now let's have a look at that particular pose and I can superimpose the pose into the figure
包含机器人，启用保持，我现在绘制特定的姿势，然后我们
that contains the robot, enable hold and I now plot that particular pose and then we
可以看到代表这个姿势的坐标框架，我们可以在这里看看。
can see the co-ordinate frame which represents this pose and we can have a look around here.
所以与这个姿势相关的位置是这个新蓝色坐标的起源
So the position associated with this pose is the origin of this new blue co-ordinate
框架，我们可以看到这个新框架的X，Y和Z轴的方向。
frame and we can see the orientation of this new frame in terms of its X, Y and Z axes.
现在我们的工作是确定机器人需要采用的关节角度，以便它的末端执行器
Now our job is to determine the joint angles the robot needs to adopt so that its end effector
与这个新的理想姿势对齐。使用反向运动学来做到这一点。有一个逆
lines up with this new desired pose. Do that using inverse kinematics. There is an inverse
与机器人对象相关的运动学方法和方法的名称是ikine，其中
kinematic method associated with the robot object and the method's name is ikine, which
反向运动学的简称，六，六自由度机器人和S因为
is short hand for inverse kinematics, six, for a six degree of freedom robot and S because
它有一个球形手腕。我传入的唯一论点是T，即齐次变换
it has a spherical wrist. And the only argument that I pass in is T, the homogeneous transformation
代表所需的姿势。
representing the desired pose.
结果是一组关节角度，如果机器人采用这些关节角度，它
The result is the set of joint angles that if the robot adopted these joint angles, it
会实现这个姿势。好吧，让我们测试一下，我们可以将我们的机器人移动到这组关节
would achieve the pose. Well let's test that, we can move our robot to this set of joint
我们刚刚计算过的角度，我们可以看到机器人已经移动了。
angles that we've just computed and we can see here that the robot has definitely moved.
现在让我们来看看这里发生了什么。所以我们可以看到中心
Now let's have a look around in here and see what's happened. So we can see that the center
现在，末端执行器的排列与这个新的坐标框架的中心对齐
of the end effector is now lined up with the center of this new co-ordinate frame that
我们介绍并且我们可以看到机器人末端执行器的X，Y和Z轴是有衬里的
we introduced and we can see that the X, Y and Z axes of the robot end effector are lined
我们刚刚介绍的蓝色框架的X，Y和Z轴。现在有点儿了
up with the X, Y and Z axes of the blue frame that we just introduced. Now it's a little
在这个简图中难以确定这个特殊机器人的配置。
difficult in this stick figure plot, to determine the configuration of this particular robot.
这是左手配置还是右手配置。是真的
Is this in a left handed configuration or a right handed configuration. It's really
有点难以分辨，但是有一种改进的方式来观察机器人，并且
a bit difficult to tell, however there is an improved way of looking at the robot, and
这是使用Plot3D方法。第一次开始需要一点时间
that's using the method Plot 3D. It takes a little moment to get started the first time
你运行它是因为它需要将一些详细的机器人CAD模型加载到工作区中。
you run it because it needs to load some detailed CAD models of the robot into the workspace.
我们在这里看到的是Puma560机器人的精美渲染图像，它非常棒
What we see here is then a beautifully rendered image of the Puma 560 robot and it's quite
清楚，机器人是左手配置，其夹持器的方向是直的
clear that the robot is in a left handed configuration and the orientation of its gripper is straight
基本上在一个可以从水平表中拾取东西的配置中。
down basically in a configuration where it could pick things up from a horizontal table.
现在我们可能有兴趣将机器人置于不同的配置中。我们可以
Now we might be interested in putting the robot into a different configuration. We can
通过重新计算反向运动学来做到这一点，但这次我们将传递一个选项
do that by re-computing the inverse kinematics, but this time we're going to pass in an option
R，其要求对应于右手配置的关节角度。
R, which is asking for the joint angles that correspond to a right handed configuration.
这是一组关节角度，我们可以绘制这些，我们现在可以看到我们的机器人
Here is the set of joint angles and we can plot those and we can see now that our robot
很明显是右手配置。
is very clearly in a right handed configuration.
现在我也可以要求它采用右手配置，而肘部则相反
Now I could also ask for it to be in a right handed configuration with the elbow down rather
而不是向上并传递选项D来表示。我们现在有一套不同的联合
than up and pass in the option D to indicate that. We have now a different set of joint
角度，你看它们与上面显示的值不同，我们可以绘制这个，我们可以
angles, you see that they differ to the values shown above and we can plot this and we can
看到我们的机器人现在是右手配置，但肘部向下
see that our robot now is in a right handed configuration but with its elbow down and
手腕确实是非常非常奇怪的姿势。看起来很尴尬。我也可以问
the wrist is in a very, very odd pose indeed. It looks quite awkward. I can also then ask
因为机器人处于左撇子配置，肘部向下，我可以绘制它
for the robot to be in a left handed configuration with the elbow being down and I can plot that
它看起来像这样......
and it looks something like this...
我们所看到的六维自由度机器人是三维运动的
What we've seen for this six degree of freedom robot that moves in three dimensions, is that
事实上，对于任何特定的末端执行器姿势，存在八种解决方案。有一个解决方案
there are in fact eight solutions for any particular end effector pose. There is a solution
在机器人处于左手或右手配置的情况下，有解决方案
where the robot is either in a left handed or right handed configuration, there is solutions
肘部向上，这意味着肘部高于肩部或在哪里
where the elbow is up, that means that the elbow is higher than the shoulder or where
肘部向下;那就是肘部位于肩部以下的位置，并且有解决方案
the elbow is down; that's where the elbow is below the shoulder and there's solutions
在翻转或不翻转手腕的地方，在配置中旋转180度
where the wrist is flipped or not flipped, that's a rotation of 180 degrees in the configuration
手腕对于带有双指夹具的机器人的情况，如此处所示，
of the wrist. For the case of the robot with a two fingered gripper, as is shown here,
然后围绕手腕轴旋转180度，有效地留下两根手指
then a rotation of 180 degrees around the wrist axis, leaves two fingers in effectively
相同的配置，在抓取物体，采摘时没有区别
the same configuration and it makes no difference when it comes to grasping an object, picking
把它放下来。
it up or putting it down.